hello it's June 23 2023 we're in active
guest stream 46.1 with Denise Holt so
Denise thank you very much for joining
we'll have your presentation first any
length of time you want and then we'll
have a discussion about some of the
topics you're bringing up and I'll read
some comments from the live chat too so
thanks again Denise looking forward to
your presentation
hi Daniel thank you so much for having
me today
um yeah so let's just Dive Right In
today I'm going to be talking about
active inference Ai and the spatial web
and uh for those who are not familiar
um there is a company called versus Ai
and they're basically uh delivering the
next generation of AI this is beyond uh
the current machine learning deep
learning models that we're all so
familiar with that are incredible tools
but really those are tools they are
great at creating content performing
tasks things like that but you know they
operate in a way that is
um you know pattern matching and they're
all siled in their ability for what they
they can do they're trained on enormous
amounts of data to increase the pattern
recognition you know and hopefully
increase accurate you know outputs but
that's really what they do
um what versus has created is something
completely different
um and it's based on active inference
and so active inference AI is entire
really new and this is the AI that will
be able to give us to uh AGI you know
leading to synthetic self-evolving
intelligence
so today
um what I'm going to be talking about in
uh this deck is
um you know active inference Ai and the
spatial web and how these Technologies
are going to affect and change the world
we'll talk about how active inference
Works within with artificial
intelligence
uh how the spatial web protocol enables
the perception and the belief updating
of the AI and how these Technologies
together enable the only AI in the world
that can run critical operations
um for systems or infrastructure smart
cities you know the planet so when
you're talking about airports hospitals
things like that
um
so yeah so let's Dive Right In
so the spatial web uh what is that
so the spatial webs being called the
network of everything basically it's the
next evolution of the internet and it's
powered by AI so this is taking us from
a library of pages and documents that we
have in the world wide web and
um oh my gosh my dog is wanting out I'm
so sorry I have to let him out
sorry about that so um
the next evolution of the internet
um now you know as I said World Wide Web
a library of pages documents
um you know everything is static
um the spatial web protocol hstp
hyperspace transaction protocol and uh
the programming language for the
protocol called uh hsml which is
hyperspace modeling language this new
protocol takes us into a library of
spaces where you know we have spatial
domains and everything within any any
space
can be locatable and programmable within
this new network
so and it's just extending the protocol
that we have now right so same internet
just more capabilities
now
um Dr Carl J friston and the versus AI
white paper and I'm sure a lot of you
are familiar with him uh the father of
active inference and the free energy
principle
now um
so versus
with uh with Dr friston has developed a
new type of AI that mimics the
self-organized systems of nested
intelligence found in nature and it's
based on his methodologies of active
inference and the free energy principle
and the spatial web protocols which I
just mentioned which were developed by
versus AI
um in December they put out a white
paper called designing ecosystems of
intelligence from first principles
and just to back up a second you know
versus created the protocol uh the hstp
and the hsml but donated it to the
public because nobody can own the
internet but they needed that in place
for what they wanted to do as a company
so that framework needed to be there so
then they also donated the protocol and
the IP to the IEEE which is one of the
largest core standards bodies that
develops everything with you know
electronics and Engineering you know
they're responsible for the core
standards around things like Bluetooth
and Wi-Fi and and things like that
so the core standards have been being
developed around the protocol for the
last almost three years and
um and yeah versus in that time has been
building you know what they've what
they've been building which I'll I'll be
talking about
so
what is a Swype paper about
um it's basically about shared
intelligence so in the white paper uh
they proposed cyber physical nested
ecosystems of distributed intelligence
joining humans machines and AI agents on
a common Network
so um
we're talking about uh
humans as integral participants uh
adaptive Behavior self-evidencing
self-organization belief updating over
several scales
um belief sharing over ensembles of
Agents so we're talking about a network
of intelligent agents and collective
intelligence and then of course the
protocols uh hstp and hsml
so
the knowledge graph and digital twins
um digital twins of our planet and all
nested systems and entities within them
um so nested ecosystems intelligent
agents both human and synthetic
sensing and perceiving continuously in
evolving environments
making sense of changes updating their
mental model and what they know to be
true and then acting on the new
information they receive
and in the white paper it's also
discussing a network of distributed
intelligence so this enables a cognitive
architecture made up of the collective
intelligence of multiple agents that
continuously communicate coordinate and
collaborate with each other
um individual and specialized
intelligences are all coming together on
a common Network
uh they're speaking a Common Language
hsml and hstp
um
it's efficient powerful cross
communication to perform tasks regulate
systems and address problems in real
time and it scales up and grows in
tandem with humans
so active inference and the free energy
principle
so what exactly is active inference
active inference is a biologically
inspired approach to AI systems as a
method for understanding Behavior
incorporating the brain cognition and
behavior modeled after the design
principles from nature and from how the
brain nervous system and the body act
and react
uh one of the questions that Dr friston
asks in this paper that is uh an
important question in reference to
active inference is you know with AI
systems you need to be able to
understand what is it that intelligence
must be given that intelligent systems
exist in a universe like ours
so active inference is a theoretical
framework that describes how agents like
people animals robots or artificial
systems can maintain their internal
States and behavior in unison with their
objectives or goals
so what is the free energy principle the
free energy principle is the theoretical
Foundation of active inference it
proposes that organisms or agents
maintain their internal States and
behavior by acting in a way that
minimizes the difference between their
current beliefs about the world and what
they expect to be true so in other words
the agents try to make things more
predictable by mitigating the difference
between what they expect to happen and
what actually ends up happening
and they do this uh by way of a cons a
continuous cycle of improving their
perception by acting on the environment
um so basically it helps to extract the
signal from the noise
and extract the regularities from the
irregularities
um so extracting the prediction error
minimizing the prediction error
and you know there are there are two
parts to this uh to this inference cycle
you know there's the perceptual
inference part uh which minimizes the
free energy by improving the internal
model to better match the sensory uh
input
um making Bayesian inferences about the
world the brain minimizes free energy by
optimizing perception so through
hypothesizing and observation in other
words the brain models the environment
better improving the perception now the
active inference part uh minimizes the
free energy by acting on the environment
so acting on the environment to reduce
the surprises the disorder or the
unpredictability and action can
indirectly influence the observation
so active inference the active inference
part of free energy minimization is
equal to lowering the surprise in the
sensory observations by acting on the
environment
actions can't directly change
observations but they can indirectly
change them by acting on the
environmental States
so then we get to active inference AI
so in the context of artificial
intelligence active inference and the
free energy principle explain how agents
can learn and adapt to new situations
and how they can generate predictions
and plan actions based on their goals or
objectives
which leads to more accurate predictions
and results which is the real goal of AI
active inference AI enables us to
overcome current limitations with
machine learning and deep learning AI
models providing a realistic path
towards artificial general intelligence
um so you know the idea is that an agent
can use active inference to minimize the
free energy and optimize Its Behavior in
a way that's consistent with its
objectives which uh
yeah which leads to more accurate AI
so the action perception Loop
um the perceptual inference and active
inference unfold continuously and
simultaneously uh underlying deep
continuity between perception and action
they're both sides of the same coin
performing the same free energy
minimization algorithm
so the free energy can be minimized by
improving the perception and then acting
on the environment in this Loop that
just keeps narrowing down the focus
and then also by learning the generative
model you know how the brain codes the
environment
um so you know that's the side that the
the spatial web protocol actually helps
with because it bakes context into every
person place or thing in any space so
that context informs the um the AI
so then it it's optimizing the expected
precision
and regulating the learning so thus we
update the model over and over to
improve our understanding of the world
and that is what the AI does as well
so how does it do this so
self-optimization and self-evolution so
active inference Ai and the free energy
principle through the Bayesian inference
allows a neural network to self-optimize
through intake and continuous updating
of new real-time sensory data while
simultaneously considering previously
established outputs and determinations
so past decisions plus the new input uh
lead to Future outcomes
um and that that cycle is a
self-optimization and self-evolution
cycle
so a self-evolving system evolves over
time
um
and current systems current AI systems
are more like a machine they're just
neural Nets that are trained to do a
specific task
but a self-evolving system is learning
from moment to moment and upgrading its
World model and thus it mimics biology
while also enabling general intelligence
So within the free energy principle
neural networks self-optimize through a
set of mathematical rules enabling Next
Generation artificial intelligence to
efficiently learn predict plan and make
decisions
um
spatial web protocol let's talk about
this
so what is the spatial web protocol
hstp hyperspace transaction protocol
it gives browsers the ability to link
spaces with an ID for every person place
or thing both digital and physical so
virtual or real
but it's much more than a location
identifier hstp is also a gatekeeper and
allows various parties the ability to
agree on who what and where anything is
in space who owns it has access to it
and what can be done with it
so hstp gives browsers the ability to
link the spaces with an ID
oh did I get this in here
so hstp is multi-dimensional query so it
allows for query over multiple
Dimensions identifying localizing and
updating the attributes conditions
excuse me contingencies and
interrelationships of objects in space
and over time
so if it can be defined and calculated
in the sphere of natural or Digital
Science it can be searchable through
hstp
so hsml this is the programming language
of uh that informs the protocol and I
like to call it the smartest contract
around
because it's it's the foundational
contract now for every person place or
thing in any space in any reality so the
only way to create a truly
technologically augmented existence is
to be able to consider and measure the
contextual elements that affect the
expression of shared information by and
between all objects in space
uh this is known as computable context
and this is what hsml hyperspace
modeling language was made for
and what are the some of the uh
contextual elements that can be
programmed
location the where the when of anything
in any space uh and you know you're
talking about you know reality the
different realities spaces time and
channels as well and then activities so
the the what and the how you know and
this is this is in regards to things
like rights and credentials or claims or
activities
and then when you're talking about
identities uh The Who and the what of
anything in any space you know you're
talking about Authority or domains or
users or assets so all of these uh all
of these uh contextual elements can
affect the expression of the shared
information by in between anything
so belief updating through context and
sensors
so hsml is a cipher for context
the spatial web which is web 3.0 the
next evolution of the internet is
library of spaces that contain objects
people places and things
these objects do things and change over
time
the context or circumstances that govern
these shifts and changes is the most
important factor to consider if we're to
understand how objects relate to each
other to people and to their
environments
hmm
so the free energy principle and hsml
the free energy principle is perfectly
suited to the programming language of
the spatial web
hsml uh the hyperspace modeling language
which enables computable context to
context based on defining recording and
tracing the changing details in physical
and digital Dimensions social Dimensions
uh meanings culture conditions
circumstances situations whether
geometrical geopolitical or geosocial by
Nature
self-evidencing and belief updating so
hsml computes context enabling the ai's
perception to understand the real-time
Changing State of anything in the world
accumulating evidence for a generative
model of one's sensed World also known
as self-evidencing
so
um
we're talking about multiple agents so
individual intelligences
and based on each agent's generative
World model unique perspective frame of
reference and nested ecosystems of these
intelligences uh and different levels of
self-organization so all of this results
in a collective shared intelligence
so uh pollen architecture and Markov
blankets
so the spatial web uh is a hollonic
structure
so active inference uh
well active inference AI within the
spatial web on the versus cosm OS
platform operates with a hollonic
structure of nested spatial domain
domains
so if you're not familiar with what a a
hollon is a hollon is where you know
something can be a hole in and of itself
and yet also be a part of something
greater so the human heart is a great
example the human hearts made of cells
each one of those cells their whole
cells in and of themselves yet they're
also part of the heart and then the
heart is a whole heart but yet it's part
of the human body so you have this
nested structure of whole parts that are
governed by the outside part but still
have this intrinsic governing going on
within itself as well
so each component is a whole element
part of the entire organism
uh their nested entities and they're
governed by the rules of the greater
influencing organism
and then uh there's they have inherited
uh
they inherit the governing and it's
passed to the internal parts that are
nested within it and each part has its
own governmental considerations for its
specific intrinsic requirements as well
so this is how the spatial web is set up
to work as well so you know when you're
talking about spatial domains you're
talking about
um you know like for instance you can
have a um
you know a restaurant that's inside of a
skyscraper building that's inside of a
city and that city is inside of a uh
State you know these nested domains
and then the active inference AI also uh
includes the principle of Markov
blankets at each level of analysis so
the mark off blankets uh Define define
boundaries acting as partitions to
mediate the interactions between the
internal and external States
um of of the spatial domains such as
like a single unit or a region or entire
you know complex Network and this
results in a self-organizing system
and a Markov blanket is just a mediator
between how things are attuned to each
other through the free energy principle
so nested domains in the spatial web
so one good example of how this may work
uh is you know if you take a factory
right so
um
you know a factory is a part of the
supply chain and uh has raw raw
materials feeding into it from various
locations
like mines or you know anywhere and then
the factory produces finished goods that
may ship to another Don another
destination like a uh Warehouse right
like a distribution warehouse
so just as that factory is an object
within a larger ecosystem of the supply
chain
um
every object within the factory belongs
to its internal ecosystem right so with
a factory you've got all the internal
ecosystem of what's going on in that
factory but yet it's still part of this
Global supply chain with you know
um uh you know raw materials being fed
into it and then it when it's done with
what it's doing it's feeding out to
other like distribution
um you know Pathways so
um you have an internal and an external
ecosystem and they simultaneously
operate according to the individual
internal and external standards the
interdependencies the in the inner
relationships so you know this is how
you can see things working within the
spatial web
so every object within the entire
spatial web network is part of an
interrelated ecosystem that feeds a
continuous stream of real-time context
between all points in space and time
this continual interaction and
communication stream takes note of all
the nuances and changes within the
relationships between all objects and
the parameters that govern them
foreign
which leads to Adaptive collective
intelligence automation so you have
programmable spaces
and uh
you know within these spaces everything
within these spaces have a digital ID
and the way the spatial web is set up is
it enables zero knowledge proofs between
all of these entities so anything inside
of any space is uniquely identifiable
and programmable with a digital twin of
the earth producing a model for data
normalization so by programming context
into everything in any space it creates
this digital twin of the space so the
spatial web becomes a digital twin of
everything
from the planet to every single system
every single object within it that's on
the network
so
um
the contingencies and changing details
inherent qualities circumstances for all
objects and situations can now be
measured and computed
uh providing a basis for the AI
perception affecting all entities and
their interrelationships uh to each
other so you're talking about adaptive
intelligence automation security through
geo-encoded governance
multi-network interoperability
and it enables all Smart Technologies to
function together on a unified system so
you know
um when you consider all of the web 3
Technologies all of the extended reality
Technologies you know AR VR
um distributed Ledger Technologies so
you have all of these technologies that
are siled and disparate this brings all
of those Technologies onto a common
unified Network now
with a Common Language between them so
it makes all of these all of these
Technologies then become interoperable
and when you're talking about Smart
Technologies when you're talking about
like The Internet of Things
um there's been no common language for
these internet of things to talk to each
other and communicate so the spatial web
brings all of the internet of things
onto the common Network now where they
become baked into this um
this network and informing the AI so all
of the data being gathered by all of
these sensors or cameras or you know the
context that's baked into the protocol
this is all the data that is now coming
together that is continually updating in
real time and informing the AI
so you have
ecosystems of nested intelligence
the design of intelligence systems must
begin from the physicality of
information and its processing at every
scale or level of organization
So within the spatial web you have ai
that scales up the way nature does
aggregating locally contextualized
knowledge bases
and acting across ecosystems and this
Maxim this maximizes efficiency
so this is the complete opposite of the
way the machine learning models work
because they're top down it's just
massive amounts of data
and you know that's what's training the
the Machine model AI
um but there's a cutoff date so then
that model now can only reference this
historical data that it's been trained
on and you know again it's just a it's
it's a pattern recognition machine the
algorithms are just to make sense of the
data that that it's been fed and how to
recognize patterns within it
um every time those models have to
compute and try to perform an output it
requires massive amounts of energy
because it still has to pull from its
Library
this massive library to try to make
sense of things now the way that the
spatial web works with the active
inference AI is you have any amount of
data
you know small amounts of data can now
be made smart because you have context
informing the AI and you have sensors
that are giving it real-time data inputs
uh to let it kind of look outward and
see what's happening in the world now
not you know referencing historical data
so this leads to minimizing complexity
so when you're talking about the machine
learning versus the active inference
um for efficiency and accuracy
the more complex a system is the more
energy it consumes so that's what I was
just referring to with all this big data
approach on these machine models
active inference in the free energy
principle naturally minimize the
complexity that's the whole idea with
the free energy principle is to minimize
the prediction error and use the
information that it can sense right so
it's taking in this the senses from from
sensors like the internet of things and
cameras and things like that but it's
also taking in what it knows about its
uh its you know the data at hand right
and it's informed
protocol the spatial web protocol with
all of the context all of the all of the
attributes around everything in any
space or any data set
so you know sensor data is noisy and
ambiguous but hsml provides Clarity with
specific and precise contextual data to
narrow the complexity and close the gap
on the free energy
so more certainty means less noise and
that each that equals free energy is
reduced faster and lower so it's a it's
a faster way to operate more efficient
and you know another point to this which
is really interesting too is that you
know most of the data that exists exists
behind uh
password walls right behind gated uh
within gated password areas right
whether it's you know on the internet
and it's all the data that people have
behind a password or whether you're
talking about like an Enterprise
organization that has all their
proprietary data that's internal you
know so
um the awesome thing about the spatial
web is that
um and the active inference AI is that
you can be within this network
and still have all of your proprietary
data gated off because the protocol
allows for that security you know it's a
it's gated at every touch point so you
can put boundaries around your
particular data but still be able to
access the the the power of the network
and the power of the active inference AI
now for your proprietary data because it
can take that small amount of data and
make it smart
so um this is a game changer for you
know access to AI for any systems in any
databases
so embodied AI
active inference uh is mimics biological
design uh and it's so it's like embodied
AI with the ability to take action and
this is the core engine of the spatial
web
so what makes active inference so
accurate
active inference is so accurate because
it continually looks outward into the
world measuring the world in real time
through a Global Network of sensors iot
devices cameras robots drones anything
that's connected within the spatial web
the digital twin network of the world
hsml informs the AI with precise data
extracts the signal from the noise
minimizing the prediction error and this
mimics the way humans and animals make
decisions
so the perception of the world
in the spatial web active inference AI
uh you know
create this creates a cybernetic
feedback loop of perception of the world
and it updates the model of the world
with the belief of what it knows to be
true gaining the understanding of the
intricacies and inner workings of the
world so that it can make decisions and
take action
okay
and it provides ever ever evolving
intelligence so the more this feedback
loop plays out the AI learns more about
the world and the results of the actions
taken just as a child learns about the
world as it grows and interacts with it
and the more accurate this AI becomes by
further updating its understanding of
the world
so um it's been described to me that you
know when versus launches their cosm
operating system and then you know which
is going to be uh later this year
uh it's going to enable everybody to be
able to build these intelligent agents
on top of the network right there they
have a
intelligent app store that's going to be
launching with the operating system so
then everybody can make these
intelligent agents the difference is
these agents so when you build an app on
say like the Apple Store app store or
Google Play You're Building a siled
piece of software right those apps are
not aware of each other they just do
whatever their function is to do the
difference is these intelligent agents
that you're building on cosm are going
to be aware of each other and aware of
the network so they're going to be
empowered with the AI and be able to act
as an agent within the the network now
it's been described to me that you know
when people are first building these a
these you know intelligent agent apps
um it's not going to be like this Stark
difference of like the power of what it
can do versus the power of what these
machine models can do because they're
all pretty it's all pretty impressive
right now but the difference is is if
you take like uh the comparison of like
a chimpanzee and a toddler at first they
seem about the same intellectually but
the difference is that toddler is going
to grow it's going to grow into a full
fledged adult it's going to continue
learning whereas that chimpanzee has
maxed out so
um so that's going to be really
interesting to watch over the next you
know a year or two is that we're gonna
see this active inference AI really
modeling the same way that humans learn
and it's going to grow in intelligence
with with this you know scores of these
intelligent agents now all working
together within the network so
now one of the really awesome things
about this too is that the active
inference AI is explainable auditable
and governable
so versus AI uh just published a
groundbreaking industry report about a
week week and a half ago called
designing explainable artificial
intelligence with active inference a
framework for transparent introspection
and decision making
so active inference is explainable AI
now how how can this be well active
inference can self-report
so machine learning models they're black
boxes uh you know and and therefore they
can't quantify their uncertainty they're
unobservable unalterable and unknowable
basically the the way the algorithm is
processing the data and coming up with
its output you
you can't see what's happening you can't
know how it's coming to its decision
it's just this black box that's
happening and there's no way to really
know what it's doing just how you know
the the input and the output
so you can't explain that now one of the
interesting things
um you know with this call for you know
putting governance around AI is that if
you have these black boxes that are not
controllable and not explainable how do
you govern that
so you know the only options have been
to you know uh either you know regulate
the the companies that are developing
these you know uh these uh tools or to
just let the free market rain now
letting free market rain is a little bit
tricky with AI because that can really
lead to like this AI arms race kind of a
thing you know for AI domination and
that that that has some risks to you
know like the
human nature right so
um and then the other problem with
regulating the the companies that are
developing these tools is that you're
asking them you're basing those
regulations off them being able to do
things like you know explain how the
results are coming you know uh to
fruition through their tools or holding
them accountable for you know
um for outputs that are you know
false or you know causing harm to
anybody or you know different things
like that which you really can't do that
either because what's happening within
these tools is not controllable it's not
auditable it's not controllable so
there's a real issue with governance
around these Machine model AIS now with
active inference AI it is completely
explainable auditable transparent and
when you're talking about the the
self-report you know active inference AI
is capable of introspection
so this enables the intelligent agents
to access and analyze their own internal
States and decision-making processes so
we get better understanding of their
decision-making process and they have
the ability to report on themselves to
basically report on how they arrived at
their decisions
um beliefs and belief updating are known
so this this dissolves the
explainability problem of the
conventional AI
and then you also have programmable
intelligence so uh versus refers to this
as code AS law
so the act of correcting a machine
occurs within the code within the
computational architecture of versus AI
system human law can now be transformed
into computable law that AI can
comprehend abide by and then act
accordingly within its decision-making
process this is a process which is fully
auditable knowable and it updates in
real time
and verses has been
um improving this concept uh in a
program called Flying forward 2020.
um
and this is a European drone project
uh the
conducted with the European Union and
you know there's eight or 12 different
countries involved I'm I'm not sure but
um basically what they've proven is that
uh they can take the the spatial web
protocol the hstp and hsml and they can
translate human laws all the laws around
like the airspace laws and you know laws
how how they shift crossing country
boundaries different things like that
um
they can take those laws
put them in a programmable uh you know
code through the protocol that the AI
within the Drone can understand and then
abide by so they've they've met with
great success through this project
um and they've they've proven that you
know these drones can deliver medical
supplies you know to a hospital Crossing
Borders uh into various air State air
spaces you know understanding no-fly
zones versus fly zones all these things
so basically human law computable that
AI can understand and abide by so when
you're talking about uh AI governance
you know
this the the protocol allows you to
actually program law that the the AI can
understand
so then the other aspect of this too is
you know humans with AI because you know
there's a lot of
um
fear baked into people uh especially in
regard to all these sci-fi scenarios
that have played out in you know
fictional books and and movies and
things like that but one of the great
things about uh the active inference AI
within the spatial web is that the AI
grows in tandem with the humans you know
because you can take programmable law
and make it to where the the AI
understands and you've got this
symbiotic relationship
um between the AI and the human it's a
network system that operates in tandem
with humans and then the AI is growing
its intelligence in sync with the growth
of humans and the world right so it
makes a controllable AI
um so in uh versus white paper
uh you know one of their opening
statements was that the the purpose of
the white paper it's denouement is a
cyber physical ecosystem of natural and
synthetic sense making in which humans
are an integral are integral
participants what we call shared
intelligence
so versus Ai and the spatial web
Foundation offer us the framework in
which we can build an ethical and
Cooperative path forward for AI and
human civilization and one thing I want
to read to you from the white paper
that's you know specific about this
um
is is this so quote we believe that
developing a cyber physical network of
emerging intelligence in the manner
described above not only ought to but
for architectural reasons must be
pursued in a way that positively values
and safeguards the individuality of
people as well as potentially non-human
persons the idea this idea is not new
already in the late 1990s before the
widespread adoption of the internet as a
communication technology a future state
of society had been hypothesized in
which the intrinsic value of individuals
is acknowledged in part because
knowledge is valuable and knowledge and
life are inseparable
that is each person has a distinct and
unique life experience and as such knows
something that no one else does
this resonates deeply with our idea that
every intelligence implements a
generative model of its own existence
the form the form of collective
intelligence that we envision can emerge
only from a network of essentially
unique epistemically and experientially
diverse agents this useful diversity of
perspectives is a special case of
functional specialization across the
components of a complex system so you
know within the the versus white paper
for this active inference AI
you know they're very clear about the
importance of uh of The Human Experience
and the various human experiences
in tandem with the growth of of the the
AI within the spatial web so I just
thought that was really important to uh
to kind of let people know
so then you have accurate World models
collective intelligence trained on
real-time data evolves making decisions
and updating its interior model based on
what is happening now not on historical
data sets active inference AI is not a
language model generating words about
the world
based on outdated knowledge it's been
fed regarding the world
active inference is like a biological
organism that perceives and acts on our
world by generating more accurate models
understandings and beliefs about our
world
these ever more accurate World models
enable better decisions a smarter world
and this is the true measure of
intelligence
so active inference AI as the operator
and this is the final section
so you have the internet of everything
the days of training AI on Big Data will
give way to an interconnected internet
of everything that deploys active
inference AI throughout the network
inherently secure and accurate because
it takes any point of real-time data and
makes it smart through an empowered
ecosystem of interconnected AI apps that
act as intelligent agents
active inference cosm and the spatial
web
active inference AI inside of the versus
AI cosm operating system has access to
the entire spatial web with iot sensors
and cameras and all context markers
attached to all objects within all
spaces within the network tracking and
identifying changes over time this AI
becomes an ecosystem of intelligent
agents that are all interoperable over
hstp
so what does this mean for the planet
active inference AI can run the planet
uh Dan Mapes who's one of the
co-founders of verses he describes the
spatial web with active inference AI as
a nervous system for the planet
together these Technologies enable the
only AI in the world that can run
critical operations for systems
infrastructures smart cities and the
planet so when you're thinking of
climate or traffic control or smart
cities or Advanced education or
hospitals or airports all of these are
critical systems that need accurate
functioning of the AI you know you
cannot rely on machine models who you
know give you plausible answers
plausible outputs that sound accurate
but aren't necessarily accurate because
they're just trained to make it sound
appropriate appropriate and accurate are
very different things so because the
active inference AI is based on
real-time data actual data context
that's baked into everything it's it's a
it's an accurate form of AI and it can
be trusted to run these critical systems
so it can be the operator
and then we come to sentient
intelligence so this is the missing
piece of the data puzzle that gets us to
artificial general intelligence we now
have the world model and we now possess
the ability for continuous and adaptive
context markers enabling a cognitive
World a cognitive model of this world
and the ability to compute awareness so
this is taking us from the artificial
narrow intelligence which is what these
machine models are to potentially
artificial general intelligence and then
artificial super intelligence because
the more the active inference AI learns
about the world uh it it can start to
question and become curious about the
world and you know it's the difference
between you know
asking the AI agent something and then
having the AI agent ask you something to
clarify what you want or what your needs
are you know it's that Curiosity back on
you that'll take us to the artificial
super intelligence
so I'm just going to close by letting
you know that versus AI their cosm OS is
going to be launching uh at the end of
the year
and uh the idea is let's create a new
world together they've created the tools
for anybody to create the AIS on top of
so
um you know it's a huge opportunity uh
they're going to be launching the beta
at the end of this year if you go to my
website Denise holt.us there's a menu
item where you can sign up for the beta
if you'd like they're going to be
selecting
um you know uh
you know
they're going to be selecting developers
and projects to be a part of this beta
so if you'd like to be considered feel
free to sign up there
and then of course I have a podcast
and it it's on YouTube or any Spotify
Apple anywhere you find a podcast but if
you'd like to learn more about this
um you know that's really my role is
I've just been educating on the spatial
web protocol and this active inference
AI so there's a lot of information on my
website there's a lot of articles on the
podcast there's just a lot of
information so that you can learn more
so I think that's it
awesome thank you
thank you Daniel all right I'm gonna
come back on uh
video
and then all right
well thank you for the
amazing presentation there's many places
to begin many uh ways to do it but again
thank you again for sharing this
information so my pleasure
I'll uh start but just asking live
stream viewers if they want to ask
anything just put it in a live chat and
then perhaps just
there were so many topics that we
brought up that yeah perhaps I can just
reflect on a few of the topics and just
kind of summarize it as as I heard it
especially where it's different from
what we've heard uh in terms of framings
on other streams where we go way more
into the technical but but there are
just so many great ways that you had of
framing what was happening okay sound
good yeah sounds great all right so
you described active inference as
biologically based and one way that uh
biologically inspired perhaps exactly
but but based upon the biological
systems and it made me think about the
way of viewing the world in terms of its
spatial connectivity
and then thinking about the world in
terms of its statistical or causal
connectivity and so when people think
about what would biologically inspired
AI look like they might think about the
actual connections amongst the neurons
in the brain or the actual connections
amongst ants in the colony but that
connectivity allows solving that problem
so if you want to solve some different
problems or some thing else you need to
learn from those structures but not copy
them verbatim and so that level of
learning that we have to pull back to
and the level of thinking
is about the agent in their engagement
with the environment and the
minimization of surprise instead of the
maximization of reward
and that's a really clear path I think
from what we can generalize from natural
intelligence
towards how we can think about what
kinds of imperatives we should design
and what design principles should be for
synthetic intelligent agents
absolutely yeah
um okay
what brought you to
this presentation like what was your way
into the spatial web or how did this
even come to be
uh he's a long time friend of mine and
um you know so I I knew when uh
he and his co-founder Gabriel Renee
who's the CEO of versus
um when they were starting verses back
in 2016 2017
um so you know I knew what I knew what
was coming and I've been kind of
watching it unfold over the last like
you know handful of years
and so then last summer
um
you know it became really clear to me
that uh you know versus was getting
close to launching to the public you
know they've been working uh over the
past you know couple of years with like
Fortune 500 companies with you know
governments and Smart City development
all over the globe they've been involved
in this flying forward project you know
they've been deep into the supply chain
they one of the first apps they created
was an app called wayfinder which is
specifically built for
um you know uh the supply chain uh
and so you know watching all of that but
then knowing it's coming to uh later
this year I was like okay there's a
transition and you know people need to
understand what's coming because you
know I've been involved in like uh you
know uh blockchain and web 3 uh for the
last you know handful of years and so
you see all these amazing Technologies
being built and all these awesome
projects but one of the biggest problems
is that they're all siled and they're
the interoperability is the biggest
struggle so you know to me it's like
okay you know these people need to know
that's this is coming and you know the
interoperability is going to be there
for you know not just within the the web
3 or the blockchain space but really all
technology really you know anybody who
has a business that is present on the
world wide web is going to want to
evolve that presence into the spatial
web just for the the empowerment of what
this Ai and this interoperability is
going to do for their business
um so I knew there was a um a learning
curve so that's really what I set out to
do was to kind of break down that
learning curve and really start to
educate people about the protocol about
the AI and about what to expect
all right great
um a few more questions again we're just
starting to explore this and so whatever
you do or don't know is all good
how will the open source nature of the
web and the ecosystem around active
inference related Technologies be
secured
so so basically you know you have to
think of the cosm operating system as
that's that's literally the operating
system that is going to enable people to
easily build with build these
intelligent agents within the spatial
web Network right so you know
um that allows anybody to come on this
network and build these build these
intelligent agents these intelligent
apps right so the beauty of it is that
the protocol itself for the spatial web
it bakes in
um
security at every touch point right so
you can program in
um
access permissions different things like
that into whatever you're building so it
really becomes individualized right you
can you can gate off to where you know
you have data that's proprietary and
then you have data that's allowed to be
accessed by the world you can you can
make it look however you want for
whatever you're building whatever your
project is and what these intelligent
apps then become is it's your
opportunity to share your knowledge with
the world right and you can share it to
whatever extent that you that you want
to you know
thanks
when talking about just a few terms I
wrote down culture ownership Authority
how do differences amongst locations and
people's
play out when there are such different
concepts of those mentioned terms and
many other terms that arose it might not
just be something like well the Drone
can go 100 feet here and 10 feet here
what about when there's different
concepts of authority and ownership and
Justice and culture
right so well so that's
that's one of the
it's one of the beauties of the world is
that you know we all have our own uh
unique
um understandings our own unique
um beliefs our own unique cultural
Traditions
um and the differing governing uh bodies
and types of government right so the
protocol needed to be built to be able
to preserve all of that you know you
don't want there to be this next
evolution of technology that includes AI
that becomes this dictatorship of you
know this is the way the world's going
to be and this is how everybody has to
operate this preserves the uniqueness
and the individuality of everybody in
any area so really the way this plays
out it's going to be able to be
customized for region for you know
um cultures belief systems you know
um
so it's like the socio-technical ability
to you know Safeguard and preserve
traditions and different things and
mindsets so
um
you know really it's it's
you know it's not going to be a
hindrance as much as it is going to be
um something that you know kind of that
preserves the beauty of of individuality
and so when you're talking about systems
like that like you were talking about
you know it's pretty much going to be
similar to where it is today you know
like you know people have the right to
the right of refusal right you know even
in a restaurant you know no shirt no
shirt shoes no service you know so
you know there's not going to be a lot
of difference with that you know and
then so when you're talking about things
like drone delivery and things like that
then you're going to have other
standards bodies that are making those
decisions to you know make things more
inclusive rather than you know kind of
silliness of you know denying people for
whatever reason
well
all right I'll ask a question from the
live chat Bert asks
thank you for the presentation
what is the limitation of implementing
this vision
is it getting people to use the
hyperspatial language or getting active
inference working right
or I'll add a secret third thing
well so so you know I I've had people
say that you know ask that with me
saying you know well what what's the
guarantee that anybody's going to you
know uh you know take part in this new
spatial web and it's you have to think
of of the way the internet has evolved
right this isn't just like this whole
separate Network that you're gonna try
to bring everybody on to it's the same
network we're already on and it's just
evolving the capabilities within that
Network so you know when you think of
the way uh the internet started you know
when you had like tcpip and the killer
app was email and then sir Tim
berners-lee created
HTTP and HTML and then you had the World
Wide Web right so it didn't get rid of
email it just enabled this whole other
capability that now people could build
websites now instead of just sending uh
you know digital messages from computer
to computer you could actually bring an
audience to your web page and engage
that way on like a property within the
network so that's all that it's
happening right now is that we're just
taking the capability from this web 2
environment that really lacks security
and it lacks protection for people and
their data and it opens up a lot of
vulnerabilities because you have to all
of the transactions are taking place the
data is Tran is is uh transacting on a
website which is the property of a
centralized organization right so what
this is doing is it's decentralizing it
now everything in any space becomes
programmable and becomes a a spatial
domain right so now you have
self-sovereign identity you have zero
trust architecture you have this ability
to program 3D spaces so it's going to be
a natural progression for people to come
you know take take advantage of this new
uh programming language to you know be
able to empower and expand what they can
do within the network we already are on
so you know the World Wide Web is like
40 billion computers now we're evolving
from just computers to spaces and
objects and everything within there so
you know it's not going to be a matter
of people getting people to do that it's
you know people are gonna go wow I can
do that and you know
it's going to be a natural progression
as far as the active inference AI it's
going to start working within the
network and it's just going to grow so
the more people are engaging uh on you
know within the spatial web Network and
the more people that are building these
AI apps and I I think if we if we look
at what's happened just in the first six
months of this year since chat GPT came
out
um with all of the you know all of the
open source and everything that's been
available as soon as it got available to
the public and now we can Tinker with it
now we can build things you've had an
explosion of development so you know
with the ability to build these these um
intelligent agents within the network
and do it very easily and have this
interoperability within the network
I just see it as we're going to have
this explosion of development so
that's of course that's my opinion but
that's what I see happening
you stake your claim that's a beautiful
thing
I'll ask another question your answer
LED perfectly to it Bert ask again in
the chat
also is there a resource where we can
learn more about how to build a
hyperspatial website
um and you know and it's not going to be
a website so
um you know it's it's as soon as the
cosm operating system launches the
the AI is going to become a tool for
building anything so the other side of
this app store where you can build an
intelligent agent is the interface the
public interface is uh an intelligent
agent called Gia and it stands for
General intelligent agent so Gia then
becomes the interface for the public of
the of the network of the the spatial
web so Gia is going to become your
personal assistant everybody's personal
assistant uh Gia will be able to
um you know act on your behalf within
the the network so you know
just like with
um
chat gpt4 and you know how you know the
AIS are starting to be able to program
right so within the spatial web the AI
is going to play an integral part in
creating your own intelligent agents in
you know doing your own
um
establishing your own presences and and
you know spatial domains and things like
that so
um I don't have a lot of detail on how
that's going to look or work but that's
my general understanding of it so I
don't think there's going to be a huge
learning curve when it comes to that
wow all right I'll go to another
question Dave asked in the chat
does versus plan eventually to expand
the inventory of element types Beyond 12
mentioned in today's presentation people
negotiate concerns that don't seem to
fit easily in this framework
[Applause]
if I can really answer that and the
reason why is because I don't I don't my
technical knowledge of what's Happening
behind the scenes is very limited so
um the answer could be yes it could be
it's already there I mean the reality is
is those those 12 uh aspects are just
you know kind of a generalized you know
idea of what you can program but when
you're talking about you know hstp being
multi-dimensional you know and you can
program in everything from like you know
temperature to you know
um pressure to you know you can you can
you can Pro if it's programmable and
definable you know in a computational
form you can you can bake it into you
know the context around whatever you're
programming so you know in that respect
it's it's pretty unlimited except for
that limitation as long as it's
measurable and definable in a
computational way
I'll try to restate that just how I
heard it because I think it's a really
important point the 12 again this could
be totally off base of I don't have any
information but the 12
components shown are kind of like fully
one way of fully showing your work but
when you really get down to the Last
Mile and the shoes on the ground
you're in the realm of the particulars
and the specific measurements at which
point complex cultural topics will be
playing out through the minute
particulars not necessarily inheriting
some stringency from a top-down ontology
if that's fair I just wanted to kind of
say it that way um yeah
okay you mentioned I think a few times
in the presentation the idea of
realities
so yeah we have our beloved cyber
physical reality and what other are the
plural realities
so basically when you think of being
able to
um
you know program the context into the
spaces right then that provides you with
a digital twin which automatically is
giving you this
um mixed reality ability right because
you know digital twin and then physical
reality this is going to open us up to
this augmented existence this augmented
reality existence that we all kind of
Envision but the foundation hasn't been
there the framework hasn't really been
there this is providing that framework
so we're gonna we're gonna see this kind
of augmented
uh reality you know future for us you
know where we're able to like cross you
know cross through mixed realities
you're going to have the virtual reality
you're gonna have the augmented reality
and then you're gonna have the physical
reality and there's there's going to be
an unlimited way of mixing that
and then the other aspect of this too is
when you talk about like virtual reality
and you talk about the metaverses and
different you know metaverse experiences
you know I think one of the reasons why
the metaverse experience has been so
lackluster is because they're siled
right now when you consider the spatial
web that's going to be able to make it
to where you can jump in and out of
these virtual reality spaces you can
actually uh take your assets from one
space to another space because all of it
then becomes interoperable over the the
network so this is going to really open
up
everything that we've been wanting to do
is gonna now be possible within this
this spatial web Network
great
all right as we kind of begin to land
the plane
um
I'll just reflect on two
or so positive aspects that that I think
are part of the vision which we will of
course await future sensory observations
to con to confirm reduce our surprise
but
in active inference what we expect is
what we prefer so if we think it's the
most likely path forward then celavi so
the first positive thing
um is that it starts from the actual
and the measurements defining things at
some defined cyber physical layer and
potentially extrapolating here but
earlier this week we had a guest stream
with MAO and Maxwell and in the quantum
free energy principle approach the brain
there is a top level decision maker
within that blanket where the buck stops
so that doesn't mean like that the brain
is not composed of
um you know as a component of part of
larger compositions but within the given
blanket there's the highest stop so
instead of handing our self
sovereigntizing ability and intelligence
to the black box
here we can start from the actual maybe
even pick up and stabilize or change
what we already have so rather than
proposing just a totally different
future that some scaling law is going to
help us get to maybe or maybe not
we start with like what we already
measure and the decisions we already
make so I very much appreciate the
pragmatism what else might you reflect
on that point
I
I think you said it well yeah
okay then the second piece was that
everyone's knowledge
is adding something
it might be a closed sample or a distant
sample on some dimension in some setting
but everyone every cognitive agent is
adding non-zero information
and there's a lot of technical details
underneath why that is the amount of
information added might be very small
for a given question but because of
differences we literally get more
perspectives so we always see better
with more perspectives if we have the
right integration approach
so that's also very powerful and it's
something that is formally true with the
math and the statistics and I think we
want it to be true for our ecosystems
right yeah absolutely you know and and
it's you know it's interesting because
um
yeah you just you wanna you wanna
preserve that the diversity of uh
information and opinion and and you know
have that accessible
for sure
awesome well
it will be quite becoming days
probably or at least again as expected
or preferred but will very much look
forward to you coming back on the active
streams as well as some technical
presentations that might help our
community and our Institute learn more
about the details or more philosophical
discussions like the whole spectrum of
learning and applying and implementing
these technologies will be really
important to characterize but for sure
it's been incredible to have you share
this first bit is there any last words
you'd like
no just thank you so much for having me
uh it's been a pleasure and uh you know
and I I will throw this out there you
know I know there's not a lot of
information uh available out there
regarding the spatial web and the active
inference AI so if anybody has any
questions feel free to reach out to me
you can reach me on Twitter or um
LinkedIn or you know it my blog You know
Denise holt.us there's plenty of ways on
there to reach me so I'm happy to answer
any questions anybody might have
all right
thank you Denise till next time sure
thanks a lot bye-bye